<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A commemoration sermon: or, A discourse on II Cor. V.I. Occasioned by the death of a most religious young lady Mary Hampson the onely daughter of Sir Thomas Hampson, of Taplow, in Bucks, ... who died August the 14. 1677. Together with a relation of her incomparable and exemplary life.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5545A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174182</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47682871</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47682871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172826</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80236)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172826)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2651:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A commemoration sermon: or, A discourse on II Cor. V.I. Occasioned by the death of a most religious young lady Mary Hampson the onely daughter of Sir Thomas Hampson, of Taplow, in Bucks, ... who died August the 14. 1677. Together with a relation of her incomparable and exemplary life.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.D. for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title enclosed within mourning border.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped and stained, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hampson, Mary, d. 1677.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, V, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Commemoration SERMON: OR, A DISCOURSE On II COR. V. I. Occaſioned by the Death of a moſt Religious young Lady <hi>MARY HAMPSON</hi> The Onely Daughter of Sir <hi>Thomas Hampſon,</hi> of <hi>Tapplow,</hi> In <hi>Bucks,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. and Bar. Who died <hi>August</hi> the 14. 1677. Together with a RELATION of her Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and Exemplary LIFE.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>October</hi> 3. 1677.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. Jane.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. D.</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s. 1678.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Honorable and moſt worthy Lady, THE Lady HAMPSON:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is ſaid of <hi>Jacob</hi> that when he came to be perſwaded that his loſt <hi>Joſeph</hi> was alive, and a great man in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> his ſpirit revived, he baniſht his Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and dried up his Tears, and joyfully reſolv'd to go down to ſee his Dear Son. Madam, you have loſt a Daughter, deſervedly as dear, and your grief is too much propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd to your loſs: But I hope</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:3"/>
            <p>you will alſo be comforted when you Conſider that ſhe is alive, and in a Happy Condition, that ſhe dwells in place much better than <hi>Egypt,</hi> and is the Favorite of a greater Monarch than ever was <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roh.</hi> I know you have reſolv'd to go up and ſee her: and if ſhe were here, I am well aſſur'd you could freely leave her to aſcend to that bleſſed Place where ſhe now expects you. Your Affliction therefore is now reduc'd only to this, That ſhe is gone to Reſt and Glory firſt, whereas you thought She muſt have followed you. This, Madam, is no great Evill, you had ſhew'd her the way to God, and ſhe hath out-run you: but you will ſoon overtake her, and then forever you rejoyce and dwell together.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:3"/>
            <p> I have writ, and ſent your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the incloſed Papers, not ſo much to honor the Memory of your moſt bleſſed Child, as to miniſter what comfort I could againſt the grief of her Abſence, both to you and to your Honorable and moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mother: Not but that both your good Meditations do far exceed mine: but becauſe in the caſe of Sorrow we generally want a Remembrancer, and, even our own Balſom applied by another hand is more healing and effectual.</p>
            <p>Why I have herein cloſed a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon which was never preached, nor never intended to be, was partly to divert your thoughts from your Grief by a comfortable Text of
<pb facs="tcp:172826:4"/> Holy Scripture; and partly to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the Method of the Oration that follows. I believe a plain Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Life of your Excellent Daughter might have been better: The Rehearſal of her vertuous Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was the beſt Praiſe ſhe could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: But I wanted particulars to compleat a full Hiſtory: and the defects of my Memory and Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation were beſt ſupplyed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed by the Rhetorical ſtyle of an Encomium.</p>
            <p>What I have done, I wiſh it may be acceptable and ſomeways ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to your Ladiſhip: and that you may not take it ill, if an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known hand indeavours to wipe the Tears from your eyes: for though
<pb facs="tcp:172826:4"/> unknown, yet the Author truly is, and accordingly deſires to ſubſcribe himſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips moſt humble, and moſt affectionate Servant</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:5"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:5"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>IF thou art pleaſed to be cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous upon the enſuing Relation, do but mend the matter with thy Life, and then I am ſure, thou wilt ſoon excuſe, and I ſhall freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg the faults of its Form and Method. 'Tis not my part I am in love withal, or would have made publick; but Hers who is the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and the Subject of this Diſcourſe. I admir'd Her much, while living, for Her great and ſingular Goodneſs, but yet more ſince She dyed, and I learnt what before I knew not, and what here I could not duly expreſs. 'Tis not unuſual to write the Lives of Perſons of great worth: and 'twould be very uſefull, if they were all as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary
<pb facs="tcp:172826:6"/> as this, and as faithfully rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>I need not therefore find Apologies for having printed this: it was to ſpare the uneaſy trouble of reading an ill hand, to that worthy Lady I offer it to, and for whom I chiefly deſigned it. I intended alſo to diſperſe ſome Copies among my friends to whom I thought it might be acceptable and beneficial too: but deſired to avoid the labor and tediouſneſs of Tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing: and withall the thing may do good, and I am not accountable to thee to whom I am not known. I need ſay the leſs upon this, for that I would have but a few Copies come out of the Preſs; if the Printer exceeds his Commiſſion to oblige the Publick, let him anſwer for it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:6"/>
            <head>A Commemoration SERMON: OR, A Diſcourſe on 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1. Occaſioned by the Death of a moſt Religious young Lady <hi>MARY HAMPSON.</hi> Together with a RELATION of her Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and Exemplary LIFE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>For we know that if our Earthly houſe of this tabernacle were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens;</hi> 
                  <bibl>2 Cor. 5. 1.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS in Navigation, Geography is no leſs uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than Aſtrology, in that all the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Dimenſions of Heaven are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd and related to the Earth: So likewiſe, in our Spiritual Voiage through this Life, the tempeſtuous Sea of this World, it is as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172826:7"/> neceſſary we ſhould ſtudy the Map of our own Earth which we carry about us, as that we ſhould look up to that heavenly Globe, whereto we are ſtearing our Courſe: We muſt underſtand the Meanneſs and Infirmity of this our preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as well as the Glory and the Perpetuity of our future Eſtate; The firſt will make us holy in our Lives, the ſecond confident in our Deaths: the Conſideration of the Miſeries and Uncertainties of this preſent Life, will make us long for a better; and the knowledg of a better life will teach us to deſpiſe the Vanities of this: when we are fully perſwaded that <hi>when this our earthly Tabernacle is diſſolved, we ſhall have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words, three things are included, and may be conſider'd.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The diſſolution of our Bodies; <hi>if our earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Comfort we have againſt it; then <hi>we have a building of God, an Houſe not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And 3ly. The Certainty of this Comfort, in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>we know;</hi> how far this our knowledge excludes all kind of doubting.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Of the firſt St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems here to make a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as if it were a doubtful matter: <hi>If our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſe be diſſolved,</hi> (ſaith he.) But this he ſpeaks by way of Conceſſion, which is a ſtrong Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172826:7"/> and not as a doubtful Poſition: 'Tis as if he ſhould ſay, As we are certain that this our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle muſt be Diſſolved, ſo do we know with the ſame Aſſurance, that we have a better and more induring Building in Heaven.</p>
            <p>And indeed, there is nothing ſo certain as the firſt, That we muſt all die; we are oblig'd to it by the very Conſtitution of our Nature: our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are Houſes of Clay, continually batter'd by Rain and rough Weather. Our Souls dwell in a Tabernacle, an earthly Tabernacle, and ſure ſuch an Abode cannot be of long continuance. A Tabernacle hath a Roof, but it hath no Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, it is an Ambulatory houſe which may be remov'd at pleaſure: Juſt ſo are our Bodies, they have a roof, they are overlaid with a thin skin, but they have no Foundation, they ſtand up on the ſand, any forcible thruſt, any Accident may overthrow them.</p>
            <p>We are not only certain that the time of our Diſſolution will come, but we are uncertain of every moment. Our earthly houſe is very weak, we are ſure it muſt fall, but if it were never thrown down till it fell of it ſelf, we might hope to foreſee its approaching Ruine: But every blaſt of Winde, every hail-ſtone, or bigger drop of Rain, may cruſh it into the flatneſs of a Grave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tres ſunt Mortis nuncii,</hi> Death is ſaid to have Three Meſſengers, either of which may come, and tell us every moment, That we muſt leave
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172826:8"/> all, and remove from hence: Accidents, Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and Old Age. There is no man, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever condition he be, but may at any time be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or forc'd away by ſome one or other of theſe <hi>Senectus praeſentem,</hi> Old-Age ſets us on the brink of our Grave, and makes our Death preſent to us. <hi>Infirmitas apparentem;</hi> Sickneſs and Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are the Prelude of our Mortality, and the Fore-runner of a likely approaching Death. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus latentem,</hi> but Accidents threaten us continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with an unſeen and unexpected End; and the number of the caſual Deaths is great, and we know not how it ſhall be with us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christians,</hi> This ſhould be ſeriouſly thought on, for 'twould be of great uſe in the whole man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of our Lives. <hi>Meditatio mortis eſt vita perfecta,</hi> Greg. Mag. The frequent Meditation of Death is the beſt Inſtrument of Holy-Living. It would prevent and cure very many Sins and Follies, if we had it oftner in our minds, That our Earthly houſe of this Tabernacle muſt be diſſolved, that our Strength and Beauty muſt be laid in the Duſt, and that our long dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling muſt be in the dark Chambers of the Grave.</p>
            <p>Who would beſtow their Cares and Revenues in the beautifying of a ruinous houſe, whoſe rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten foundation doth ſink continually? and were it not that men will not be ſerious, how could they ſpend their whole Time and Eſtates in ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and pleaſing their Bodies, whoſe origine is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172826:8"/> from the Earth, whoſe matter is but Clay, whoſe End is Corruption, which ſink and decay every day, and cannot be kept from Diſſolution.</p>
            <p>It is writen of <hi>John</hi> the Charitable Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> that he built to himſelf a fine Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but left it unfiniſh't, and commanded that his Servants ſhould daily put him in mind to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh what he had began: that ſo being frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembred of perfecting his Tomb, he might think to fit himſelf for it, and always have Death in his thoughts. Happy were it if we alſo could find out ſome Art daily to put us in mind of our latter end. We cannot all build a Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, as the Patriarch; no, but we all carry the Corps that muſt be laid in. This our earthly houſe muſt be diſſolved, and every thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by 'tis now preſerv'd is near a kin to Death. We have many Remembrancers of our frailty, if we would liſten to their voice and mind their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and truly 'tis more a wonder that our bodies, weak as they are, ſhould indure ſo long, than that they ſhould at laſt be diſſolved: for being made of ſo many various parts, and joyned together with ſo ſmall Ligaments, and the whole being but dirt, 'tis next to a Miracle they ſhould tumble up and down ſo long and not fall to pieces. <hi>Eliphas</hi> in <hi>Job</hi> 4. 19. gives us this Deſcription of mens frailneſs and their ſtupidity; that <hi>they dwell in houſes of clay; whoſe foundation is in the duſt, and are cruſhed before the Moth; they are deſtroyed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from morning to evening, they periſh for ever without</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172826:9"/> 
               <hi>any regarding it; doth not their excellency which is in them go away? they dye even without wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure if ſuch men as are ſenſual, proud and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetuous, would now and then walk in a charnel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and there take an account of thoſe gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deurs and pleaſures, which are the worſhipped Idols of the world, it is not to be thought but that it would alay the heat of their unruly paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, abate their ſinful deſires, and reduce them to ſome Sobriety.</p>
            <p>There is much to be learn't from that voice, which the Prophet was bid to cry a loud, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 6. <hi>All fleſh is graſs, and all the goodlineſs thereof is as the flower of the field.</hi> For as the ſtrongeſt ſtalk, and faireſt colour of flowers, keeps them not from fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and being ſoon dried up and withered: ſo the ſtrength and beauty, and all the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men, are no ſecurity againſt the diſmal change of Death; ſtill they return to their firſt duſt, <hi>we muſt be as water ſpilt on the ground, which is not gather'd up again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, that our hearts might not be lifted up, by any of thoſe outward ornaments, we obſerve in Scripture, that ſeveral perſons who had been allow'd the largeſt Portion of thoſe natural en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, died ſooneſt, and in the worſt manner: The ſtrongeſt <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the fair <hi>Abſalom,</hi> the ſwift <hi>Aſael,</hi> the wiſe <hi>Achitophel,</hi> they all came to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural end; they were thrown in the duſt, by violence and force. So true it is of all men, even the ſtrongeſt, what we read <hi>Job.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Man that</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172826:9"/> 
               <hi>is born of a Woman, is of few days and full of trouble, he cometh forth as a flower, and is cut down, he flees alſo as a ſhadow, and continueth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude this firſt point, by applying to this matter the diſſolution of our bodies, St. <hi>Peters</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, in another caſe. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Seeing then that all theſe things muſt be diſſolved,</hi> all theſe members and comely parts of our bodies, <hi>what manner of perſons ought we to be, in all holy converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Godlineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now conſider'd the ſad Ruin and Fall of this our earthly Houſe, let us ſee in the ſecond place, what comfort we have againſt it.</p>
            <p>How will it be with us after the Diſſolution of our fleſhly Tabernacle? when this our priſon, our veſſel of clay is fallen to peices, then <hi>evadit intus recluſa columba:</hi> our Soul flies away and goeth to reſt; there is a building of God, a bleſſed recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle fitted to receive it.</p>
            <p>We are not left to the uncertainties of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, <hi>animula vagula blandula,</hi> &amp;c. Dear ſoul, where art thou a going to wander in unknown places. No, our Bleſſed Lord Chriſt by the Goſpel, hath brought to light, both life and immortality, and praiſed be his goodneſs; <hi>We know that when our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle is diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There cannot be a greater comfort for a man forc't out of a poor Cottage, than to be promis'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172826:10"/> he ſhall be receiv'd in a glorious Palace; For one that is driven out of an earthly houſe, to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd he ſhall dwell in heavenly Manſions.</p>
            <p>'Tis true the houſe muſt fall, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſhall be diſſolved: but then the in-dweller ſhall eſcape, and inſtead of a Tabernacle of clay, ſhall enter a City of Gold and Saphirs; <hi>a building of God, an houſe not made with hands eternal in the heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe laſt words are capable of a twofold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and may ſignify, either the Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of heaven, or elſe our own Bodies, after our glorification. For as ſure as our Creed is true, ſo true it is there will be a Reſurrection; God hath plainly revealed it, and we firmly believe it. And ſo by faith we know, that our Bodies ſown in diſhonour, ſhall be raiſed in glory; they are ſown in weakneſs, but ſhall be raiſed in power; they are ſown natural Bodies, but ſhall be raiſed ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual bodies; This corruptable ſhall put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and this mortal ſhall put on immortality, and Death ſhall be ſwallowed up in Victory. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Out of the duſt of theſe our vile Bodies God will raiſe a new habitation for our Souls, beautiful and glorious, beyond what we can think. And ſo the Text ſaith, not that our Bodies ſhall periſh for ever, and be reduced to nothing, but, only they ſhall be diſſolved, they ſhall crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into duſt, but God knows and takes care of the leaſt part of it: and when it is refin'd and cleanſed from the infection of ſins, God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172826:10"/> it into a body, glorious and bright, as the light of Heaven; <hi>the Righteous ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun, in the glory of their Heavenly Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be the ſence of the words, That this buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of God be meant of our glorified Bodies, then this is a great and ſpecial comfort, which we Chriſtians have; that God doth with our Bodies in our Death, as with our Souls in our Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: When in our ſincere return to God, we yield our minds and affections to him, he renews and ſanctifies them, and makes them holy and capable of his favour, and bleſſed enjoyment: And ſo when we ſubmit to our portion of duſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our Bodies to God, he deſtroys their blemiſhes and imperfections, he beautifies them, and makes them impaſſible, glorious and immortal, fit to dwell in Heaven, in the Society of Saints and Angells.</p>
            <p>But then, this building of God, this Eternal houſe in the Heavens, may be underſtood alſo of the bleſſed Manſions of Glory, wherein holy Souls are received, after their departure out of this mortal life. For though it be controverted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Souls of the Faithful be admitted into the ſame glory wherein they ſhall enter after the great day of Judgment: or whether there be other receptacles for them, till the Reſurrection? yet it is generally agreed on by all, but the late inventors of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> that they are in a ſtate of Reſt, in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſom, full of comfort, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hopes, and paſſionate longings for the time of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172826:11"/> their reunion, and their conſummation. And we are warranted to ſay by the Scripture, and by the Church, the beſt interpreter of it, That the Souls of the Faithful, after they are delivered from the burthen of the Fleſh, are in joy and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity. And ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>v. 8th. We are confident and willings, rather to be abſent from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and to be preſent with the Lord.</hi> whether in the outward Courts, or in the inner Sanctuary, it matters not to know. Happy are they who are preſent with the Lord, in whatever part of his Houſe it be.</p>
            <p>There they ſee, hear and injoy, what, in this World, Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor Heart conceived. They begin to drink and to plunge themſelves in that Ocean of Bliſs, which is called <hi>Eternal Life;</hi> which I cannot deſcribe, and which you could not comprehend.</p>
            <p>But O bleſſed Manſions of the Bleſſed! Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal houſe in the Heavens! Glorious building of God! how ſhall we underſtand whilſt in this vale of miſery, the exceeding great ſtatelineſs, the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful glories, and the moſt pleaſant deliciouſneſs of thy pleaſures and beauties?</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral words in the Text, which lead us very far in this bleſſed enquiry, if our thoughts, and our time were not too much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd. But if we caſt an Eye upon our dwellings here below, we ſhall ſoon underſtand how much we ſhould value and deſire everlaſting habitations above.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172826:11"/>
            <p> There be three places wherein we ſojourn before we come to our Eternal home, the firſt is appointed by Nature, the Womb, wherein we live like plants, without either ſenſe or reaſon. The ſecond is ordered by Providence, the World, wherein we live in trouble and miſery, expoſed to many dangers and ſorrows. The third was built by Sin, the Grave, Chambers of Death and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wherein we dwell with Worms, Corruption, the ruin and diſhonour of our own Nature. I ſay, view theſe, which are <hi>domus incolatus,</hi> the houſe of our Pilgrimage and ſojourning, and compare them with that Eternal houſe in the Heavens, wherein God dwells, and whereof he is Maker: then you ſhall in ſome manner underſtand how much Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven excells all theſe earthly Priſons, and ſhall be mov'd to ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>How amiable are thy Dwellings, thou Lord of Hoſt! My Soul long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O! how great is the difference betwixt the place of our Conception, and the immenſity of Heavenly regions! betwixt our houſes of clay, and the Houſe of God! betwixt the Priſons of Death, and the Land of everlaſting Life!</p>
            <p>But I need ſay no more upon this Subject, here is comfort enough to them that believe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Chriſt, when he aſcended to glory, <hi>John</hi> 14. 1. <hi>I go to prepare a place for you.</hi> Here is, I ſay, comfort enough againſt all our ſorrows, that when we leave the uneaſy abode of this our earthly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172826:12"/> Tabernacle, we ſhall be recieved into heavenly Palaces, here are inducements enough to deſpiſe this wretched World, and ſigh after our better Country, where we are promis'd reſt and joys that ſhall have no End.</p>
            <p>I conclude this ſecond Point with the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Peter, Therefore beloved ſeeing that ye look for ſuch things,</hi> for ſuch a glorious houſe, ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Manſions, <hi>be diligent that</hi> whenever God calls for you, <hi>you may be found of him in peace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot and blameleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing to be conſidered, is the certainty of this comfort, in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>we know,</hi> how far this our Knowledge excludes all kind of doubting.</p>
            <p>We know indeed, that there is a reſt, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things prepared for the people of God; we know it by the certitude of Faith; all thoſe many convincing arguments that prove the Goſpel to be true, and JESUS to be the Son of God, makes it indubitable. For this is the great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which God ſent his own Son to Preach, proportioning the Meſſage to the Meſſenger, <hi>This is the redord,</hi> ſaith St John, <hi>that God hath given us E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life, and this life is in his Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, God hath ſufficiently atteſted, to ſatisfy all men that ſo it is: and St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the Text is very confident, <hi>we have a building of God</hi> (ſaith he) and <hi>we know it;</hi> we know that if our earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle be diſſolved, we have an Eternal houſe in the heavens. He is altogether poſitive, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172826:12"/> makes no doubt of the matter; and we may rely upon his credit: for it was by the ſtrongeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions that he was made to credit this truth; and afterwards he ſuffer'd the greateſt of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to propagate it. Many other Witneſſes alſo have ſealed the ſame with their own blood: but wherever the Goſpel is imbrac't, this is likewiſe received without objection.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion therefore, is not whether or no the thing be true; though the arguments be but morally demonſtrative, as being a matter of Fact, yet generally Chriſtians do all aſſent to it: I am ſure all good Chriſtians do, and to them I now wholy addreſs my Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The doubt with them is not about the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of any Promiſe, or of this Scripture in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: but about the particular application of it; ſhall I my ſelf enter into thoſe glorious Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? many that have a good and tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and as to the real event, are undoubtedly ſafe, yet have fears upon them: and ſometimes from thoſe fears, draw ſad inferences.</p>
            <p>They doubt not of Gods truth, whether or no there be ſuch a glorious Manſion and happineſs for us, as he hath revealed: but they queſtion themſelves, whether they are fitted for't; whether they have done, or ſhall do, what ſhould qualify them for Heaven. And in this caſe, I ſay, that that fear may be an allay to our joys: but except it be very ill manag'd (which a ſpiritual Guide could eaſily prevent) it cannot be a prejudice to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172826:13"/> our finall ſafety. I ſay more, that timerouſneſs in them that have moſt reaſon to be confident, many ſometimes do much good, be an incentive to care, and greater watchfulneſs: and yet beyond this I may add, that it is even a duty.</p>
            <p>I am ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of himſelf, as being afraid of becomming a caſt-away, after he had Preach't to others: and he gives us this general command, Heb. 4. 1. <hi>Let us fear, leaſt a Promiſe being left us of entring into his reſt, any of you ſhould ſeem to come ſhort of it.</hi> So that, moſt certainly, fear is not deſtructive of our better hopes: but is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a motive to work out our Salvation with the greater care and humility, <hi>and to give all diligence,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts, <hi>to make our calling and election ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is not a place to diſpute with them that teach men to preſume, or that plunge them into doubts, and perpetual ſcruples: but to be brief, I lay this of St. <hi>Aug.</hi> As a Poſition not to be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>nunquam mala mors putanda eſt quam bona preceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vita,</hi> a good Life can never end but in a happy Death; ſecure the firſt, and then undoubtedly the ſecond will follow: as for ſuch fears and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, as may aſſault us, whilſt we are in the ſtate of miſery and imperfection, we muſt let them paſs by, and go on minding our duty. For ſure it is that ſo it was with others before us, even with the deareſt of Gods Children. They have not always been equally ſenſible of ſpiritual comforts; ſometimes they were under the cloud, full of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172826:13"/> grief and ſad apprehenſions. It was ſo once with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 77. And likely it hath been ſo with all good men, ſome one time or other, or perhaps often.</p>
            <p>For indeed, we are for the moſt part in this life, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Priſon, <hi>Act</hi> 12. 9. when God ſent his Angel to deliver him from a great and imminent Danger, <hi>he thought he ſaw but a Viſion, and wiſt not that it was true, what was done by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> till he came to himſelf, after he was paſt the Iron gate, and then he underſtood Gods gracious purpoſe to his own ſafety. And ſo, we generally are not ſenſible of what God hath already done, and is further doing to make us happy: and we ſhall have but imperfect notices of it, and ſhall be but as in a Dream, till we are alſo paſt the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron gate of Death: but then we ſhall wonder at our dulneſs, and ſhall be tranſported with raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of joy, when we come to underſtand the deſign of God's Providences towards us, and are admitted to ſee face to face, that which we now behold but darkly, and in a Miſtery. Let us therefore at preſent take no further care, but to obey and follow, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did, and though we go trembling, and heavily, yet at laſt we ſhall come to joy and ſafety, as he did.</p>
            <p>The fearful Paſſenger in the Ship, is drowned never the ſooner becauſe he fears it: and the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Chriſtian in the Church, will be ſafe enough, thou he be not ſecure.</p>
            <p>We have all the reaſon, and all the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172826:14"/> in the World, intirely to caſt our ſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God; into the Arms of the holy JESUS, who will in no wiſe caſt out any that humbly comes to him: and who requires no more of us, than what we ſincerely can do. God is infinitely good, and he hath done ſo much to aſſure us of his mercy and loving kindneſs, that we cannot but admire his Condeſcention, and rejoyce that we depend upon him, who <hi>would have all men to be ſaved;</hi> and hath therefore purchas'd Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for all, at a mighty rate; and hath ingag'd all ways poſſible, that if we heartily deſire and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after Salvation, we ſhall without fail ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it.</p>
            <p>Let us not then attend to our Fears, and the perplexed thoughts of our own minds, let us but take care to ſecure our duty, by a hearty love and obedience, do all we can to ſerve and to pleaſe God, and we are certainly happy: and he will refreſh us with as much comfort as we need, to carry us through this vale of Tears.</p>
            <p>A Marchant ventures his Eſtate, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſome are grown rich; A Souldier will hazard his Life, becauſe ſome have eſcapt the edge of the Sword, and reaped a ſprig of Laurel: and ſhall we be afraid to truſt our Souls with God, our faithful Creator, and gracious Redeemer, when from ſuch a truſt, we expect the greateſt glory and happineſs.</p>
            <p>The time was when we were nothing, and he made us; the time was when we were as though
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172826:14"/> we had not been, living without ſence or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in our Mothers Bowels, and God brought us to this light. Every change hath been for our advantage; firſt nothing, and then a being, and then a more perfect being: and why ſhould we doubt but that after our next change, our diſſolution, we ſhall be yet better.</p>
            <p>God hath now over us as much power, as in the State of Separation: but then he will ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more gratious, confirming the Pardon of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry repented Sin, and aſſigning a recompence to every good work. And then what can we fear? not the ſtrangeneſs of the change, for 'tis imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible; <hi>Mors eſt depoſitis ſarcine gravis,</hi> Death is onely the laying down of a heavy burthen, the returning of each part of man to its own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the Body to the Earth whence it was, and the ſpirit to God who gave it. There is no ill in this.</p>
            <p>Neither yet can we fear the ſtrangeneſs of the unknown Regions of Spirits, for we are in God as an Atome in the Air, as a drop of water in the Sea; the immenſity of his Divine Eſſence doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow us; we can be no where but in God, <hi>Though I ſhould paſs through the vally of the ſhadow of Death, I will fear no evill,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) for thou art with me.</hi> Beſides Death is <hi>via tria,</hi> a beaten path, all mankind have paſſed through it, yea, and the Saints of God, and the Bleſſed JESUS himſelf, who hath made the paſſage ſafe and eaſy for all his followers.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:172826:15"/>
            <p> But I'le tell you Chriſtians, what you muſt do, that you may not be afraid of Death, and the diſſolution of your earthly Tabernacle. You know that the day-labourer looks with joy upon thr Sun-ſetting, becauſe then he receives his hire: The Traveller is glad when his journy draws to an end, for then he comes to home &amp; reſt. Do for Eternity what theſe do for things temporal; labor for heavenly reſt, advance towards it in the ways of Vertue and Godlineſs: and when you come near the end of your race and of your labours, and come to have a near proſpect of your Crown and your happineſs, then your hopes ſhall be ſtrong, and your Comforts great, and the Text that lays before us ſhall be to you a ſpring of joys, you ſhall then be able to ſay with great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, <hi>We know, that when our earthly houſe, of this Tabernacle is diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <p>I Long'd to have done with the Text, that I might turn mine eyes upon that bleſſed Saint, whoſe Vertuous Life, I now come to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. The Text indeed abounds in Conſolations, but her Example is full of Inſtruction, and her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Life declares the Comfortable Doctrines of the Text, far better than my Diſcourſe could do.</p>
            <p>That there ſhall be a Diſſolution of our earthly Tabernacle, ſhe preach'd by her Mortification,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172826:15"/> Self denyal, and Contempt of the World.</p>
            <p>That there are heavenly Manſions prepar'd to entertain pious Souls after their departure, her Devotion and Heavenly-mindedneſs are ſtrong Arguments.</p>
            <p>And how to get this joyful knowledg, the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of a place for our ſelves in the Houſe of God, ſhe hath taught us by her Goodneſs and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and all thoſe her Chriſtian Vertues, for which ſhe is now bleſſed and rewarded above, and deſerves here to be praiſed and admired, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and imitated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MARY HAMPSON,</hi> of whoſe Noble De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent I might ſpeak great things; For ſhe might have ſaid with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that ſhe had whereof to glory according to the fleſh, as much as any could boaſt of, but ſhe rather choſe, as that great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, to value none of thoſe outward advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in compariſon of the excellency of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Knowledge of Chriſt. She valued her Chriſtian-name, though it were common, much above her honorable Sir-name, which in the World would have brought her more reſpect.</p>
            <p>And indeed, the Nobleſt Title of a Chriſtian is deriv'd from his Second Birth, and Hers was ſo: For in the Sacrament of Regeneration ſhe really paſt into Gods Family, and in Truth did become his Child, and an Inheritreſs of his Heavenly Kingdom. She made this appear afterwards as <hi>Mary</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>by chuſing the beſt part,</hi> the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172826:16"/> Word and Favor of JESUS above all the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and imployments in the World. And, like <hi>Mary Magdalen, ſhe alſo loved much,</hi> and gave great demonſtrations of it: And though we cannot ſay, That ſo much was forgiven her as the Penitent <hi>Magdalen,</hi> becauſe God had preſerv'd her in great Innocence; yet we may ſay, That as ſhe loved much, ſo, much was given her, for God betimes bleſt her with a mighty Grace, and from her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy ſhe aſpir'd, and fitted herſelf for Glory.</p>
            <p>This appears not only by her Vertuous Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and Towardlineſs, and her Proficiency in the Chriſtian Knowledg, when ſhe could only, as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>balbutire Chriſtum,</hi> ſtammer out the name and the things of Chriſt: but alſo by ſeveral Queſtions about Heaven and the Glories thereof, and ſuch Reflections upon them, as exceeded as much the capacity of her tender Age, as they came ſhort of that higher knowledge which ſhe hath now attain'd.</p>
            <p>'Tis true ſhe had great Advantages in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and beſt of Inſtructions, ſhe had from her excellent Parents, from whoſe pious Care ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd thoſe Seeds of Vertue which afterwards did ſo much fructify; The Pains and Prayers of thoſe moſt Religious perſons could not but have a good effect in the Education of a Child born to God and Goodneſs: but it muſt be granted that it was the work of a ſpecial Grace made thoſe Means ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual; <hi>Paul may plant, and Apollo may water, but God gives the Increaſe:</hi> And an Increaſe here was ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172826:16"/> great that I know not where to begin to tell the fruits of it.</p>
            <p>When I look into the time of her riper years, I ſee ſo large a field open before me, that I loſe my thoughts in its ſpaciouſneſs; and though all things in it look amiable and pleaſant, yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but enter it trembling, knowing, that to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion every thing therein remarkable and worthy our Obſervation, exceeds as much my poor Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as to expreſs, according to the dignity of the matter, what I ſhall note and repreſent.</p>
            <p>Such were the Fears of St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzene,</hi> when he was compoſing the funeral Oration of his own Siſter, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>I am not afraid</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of exceeding, but of maiming the Truth, left a lame and imperfect Commendation, reflect diſgrace upon her, who juſtly, deſerves the greateſt honour.</hi> This is my caſe. I know that my undertaking is above my ſtrength: but yet pitty it is that ſo great, ſo fair a Vertue ſhould be buried in an obſcure Silence. If I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not draw her to the Life, whom God made ſo lovely, and ſo inimitable, yet I hope that my ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der draught will reflect ſome Glory to God, who himſelf made the Original ſo perfect: Thereby alſo I deſign to provoke others to Imitation, to coppy this ſo fair and ſo attractive an Example: And however, <hi>The Righteous ſhall be had in everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Remembrance,</hi> Praiſe and a Memorial is juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly due to him: and if I cannot pay the debt, yet I own it, and here offer my poor acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:172826:17"/>
            <p> To proceed with ſome order in the ſhort defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Account I ſhall give of the life of this Noble and Vertuous Lady; I muſt, as it were break the golden Chain, and divide thoſe Vertues of hers, which were ſo cloſely link't together, into three ſeveral Orders, according to the Partition of St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, put thoſe that regard our ſelves, under the name of <hi>Sobriety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Second I ſhall place thoſe Vertues which are exercis'd towards our Neighbour, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe in the laſt, which more particularly do belong to God and are therefore called <hi>Godlineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes ſo, for except we learn to deny, and in many things overcome, our ſelves, we can neither be juſt to our Neighbour, nor diſcharge our Duty to God.</p>
            <p>This therefore our dear Saint laid as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of her high and heavenly Virtues, ſhe was very eminent in all the Duties which are reduc'd to this head.</p>
            <p>It was not with her as 'tis generally with young People; they commonly live many years by Senſe, before they be ſo much as capable of ſober Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, <hi>firſt, that which is natural, and afterwards that which is ſpiritual,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle himſelf, Cor. 15. The ebulition of the youthful blood and the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sker ſpirits muſt be a little over, before Reaſon and Religion can enter and rule the Paſſions, and the Natural Appetites. But of her I may ſay, That
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172826:17"/> ſhe had more of the Angel than of the Fleſh in her: For ſhe was grown a ſtrong Chriſtian before ſhe came to the ſtrength of Nature: She had maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and brought under ſinful Motions, and all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual deſires, before her joynts were fully knit or her grouth compleated.</p>
            <p>A woman in our vicious age is called Vertuous if ſhe hath not proſtituted herſelf to the baſeſt Luſts. But, Lord, at how great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance did This young and ſpotleſs Virgin ſtand from them! ſuch foul Temptation could not have dar'd to look upon a face of ſo much Modeſty: ſhe had too many excellent Vertues, like ſo many Tutelar Angels, to keep her from ſuch deadly ſins; her Soul was pure and heavenly, and her body bleſt with ſuch a gueſs, could not but be chaſt and Sanctifyed; and indeed, ſhe not only abſtained from unlawful pleaſures: but ſhe alſo refrained her ſelf from many permitted enjoyments.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Mundus Mulibris,</hi> that vain and tireſom attire, which is now the Study and the Pleaſure of Perſons of her Age and Birth, was neither her employment, nor leſs her delight; what her qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity did require ſhe wore for decency: but ſhe had better Ornaments than could be borrowed from her outward Apparel.</p>
            <p>The affectation of any ſingularity was far from her meek and humble Spirit, therefore ſhe ſubmitted to what was fit for her: but ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd the time of her dreſſing by Reading and Meditation, and whileſt others were employed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172826:18"/> about her body, her Soul was waiting upon God.</p>
            <p>The Tyrant Laws of Cuſtoms and Faſhions, ſhe could not altogether neglect, and ſhe had where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to exceed them, had it been her deſire: but ſhe had a better Lord than the World: and it was her choiſe and paſſion to do his work, and to ſpend upon him her time and her money, as much as was poſſible.</p>
            <p>This was not out of Diſcontent nor Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor that ſhe had any reaſon to fall out with the Gayties of the World, there was nothing of humour in it: it was her free choiſe and ſerious conſideration, and therefore it was her conſtant courſe; ſhe preſerved a cheerful and contented Spirit, being well pleaſed with her Condition, and having great reaſon to be ſo: only her Joy conſiſted not in gaudy toys, or a looſer laughter.</p>
            <p>God had made her Body well ſhap'd, her face comely, without any defect of proportion or complexion, with a ſweet, and yet reſerved and grave Countenance; she needed not envy others, nor any ways endeavour to mend or alter what God had made her: and she was far enough from it; she much abhorr'd thoſe Arts and Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons found out for to palliate defects, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to vanity.</p>
            <p>It might be ſaid of her as of St. <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, her red paint was a graceful modeſty: and her white her abſtemiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>For indeed, abſtemious she was in a high De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172826:18"/> ſhe kept under her Appetites, as well as her Paſſions: her mind and her body were equally ſubdued to Reaſon and to Religion, to the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt temperance and mortifyedneſs.</p>
            <p>Thoſe faſting-days the Church appoints, and which devouter Chriſtians ſpend in Penitential Devotions, ſhe without fail Religiouſly obſerv'd, with great ſeverity to her ſelf, and yet endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring what ſhe could, not to be noted. Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial was more pleaſing to her than the gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſenſe can be to Voluptuous Perſons, if ſhe were free from outward Afflictions, yet ſhe would prove herſelf a lover of the Croſs, if that may be called a Croſs which was her Delight, to deprive her ſelf upon Religious accounts, of Lawful Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; to offer to God her natural deſires and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites as a Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>Lord, where ſhall we find ſuch Chriſtians! how few are they who thus, by wiſe and pious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, can guide their affections, and deſpiſe all Worldly Vanityes, and reject Bodily pleaſures, and no otherwiſe exceed the due bounds of ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, than by being too ſtrickt and too Mortify'd?</p>
            <p>Bleſſed Soul, thou wert here Dead and Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the World! thou didſt feed upon Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Manna, and the thoughts of Eternity! thou wert Covetous of nothing but Grace and Vertue! thine ambition was to be dear to God, and fair in the eyes of Heaven! thy delight was to bear the yoke of Chriſt, and to follow his ſteps! Thou wert here a way-faring Paſſenger, uſing what ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity required, as ſtill going forward,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172826:19"/> advancing towards that Bleſſed home, whether now thou art happily come!</p>
            <p>And now Chriſtians, ſuppoſe ſhe had indulg'd her ſelf, in thoſe fond enjoyments, generally do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on by young People; ſuppoſe ſhe had had all the Fineries and all the Dainties in the World; where would now the advantage of it be? Muſt not thoſe mean tranſitory pleaſures have ended with her life, If not before it? doubtleſs they muſt: but the rewards of her ſober Virtues are great, and laſting for ever For her moderation and her ſelf denial in Temporal pleaſures, ſhe now takes her full of thoſe Diviner Joys, which are Eternal but they are Secret.</p>
            <p>O Truly Wiſe and Happy Child! thou didſt betimes Learn the hardeſt Leſſons of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Philoſophy! Thou wert perſwaded there are better things in Heaven for the followers of JESUS, than this Earth can afford! and thou didſt chuſe and act accordingly. Thou wert made Wiſe unto Salvation, before the inticements and follies of the World could deprave their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or ſeize upon thine affections! and now Bleſſed art thou, and Bleſſed alſo ſhould we be, if we could, or would follow thine Example.</p>
            <p>But I can not diſplay all the Beauties of it. I muſt every where omit and haſten and now paſs to the ſecond head, to ſpeak of thoſe Virtues which are comprehended under the name of Righteouſneſs. They are ſuch as are exerciſed towards our Neighbors, in their ſeveral Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to us: and in theſe, ſhe was alſo very exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, and very eminent.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:172826:19"/>
            <p> Self-Love and Intereſt are things that make men partial againſt others, where themſelves are concern'd, but the having ſo intirely ſubdued thoſe evil Affections (as I have ſhewed before) there was nothing in her to obſtruct her Juſtice and her Charity,</p>
            <p>To her Parents therefore ſhe was a dutyful and loving Child; ſhe was tender of all that concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and ſought nothing but to bring them as much Comfort and Joy as a truly good Child can bring to good Parents: ſhe exceeded what they deſired in obſervance to them: and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing they could chide her for, was this, That ſhe was not kind enough to her ſelf.</p>
            <p>To her other Relations she was dear alſo, and she paid to them all, all that Reſpect and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which they could any ways challenge or deſire; she was much concern'd for their good, and where otherwiſe she could not by Prayers, she expreſt her true kindneſs to them; having learnt as St. <hi>Paul</hi> taught Chriſtians, <hi>to ſhew firſt Piety at home.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
            <p>Many there are who when they come abroad, ſeem very meek and obliging; they put the beſt ſide outward, and are very courteous to Strangers: but at home they are churlish and ungentle, angry and froward; There they are pleaſed with nothing, and they pleaſe no Body; their Language and their Behavior are harsh and vexatious, and this is a fault as great and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, as it was far from the temper of this Bleſſed Chriſtian.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:172826:20"/>
            <p> She had learnt of her Bleſſed Maſter, to <hi>be meek and lowly:</hi> and of the great Apoſtle, <hi>to be gentle, eaſy to be intreated full of Mercy and good Fruits,</hi> and ſhe therefore was moſt eſteemed where ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed moſt: ſhe was beſt Beloved where ſhe was beſt known.</p>
            <p>She not only made no breaches her ſelf in the Family where ſhe lived, but ſhe endeavour'd to cloſe them up, as faſt as others did make them, ſhe was not only Peaceable, but a Peace-maker; and in this ſhe ſhewed her Wiſdom and her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, as much as her good will: for ſhe had not only the Innocence and Meekneſs of a Dove, but the Prudence of the Serpent alſo.</p>
            <p>She had alſo learnt and practic'd another great and difficult leſſon, <hi>to take heed to her ways that ſhe might not offend in her tongue;</hi> a leſſon as uſeful and neceſſary, as it is generally neglected. That Tongue wherewith ſhe ſo often Bleſt God, ſhe would not abuſe to his diſhonour, to vain babling, or to her Brothers prejudice: that made her keep ſilence, when many were talkative and loud. She could have ſpoke as much as they, with as much grace, and to better purpoſe: but ſhe would have diſcours'd upon better Subjects than impertinent News, or uncharitable Stories.</p>
            <p>But it was not only her care to hurt no Body: She could alſo ſeek and joyfully embrace all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to do good to others: she would vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the ſick; exhort and comfort them; pray with them and for them: and many ways make it appear that her Charity reach'd the Soul alſo, though it was not confin'd to it.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172826:20"/>
            <p> Not confin'd to the Soul, I ſay: for ſhe was as forward to relieve the outward wants of needy perſons, as to promote the Spiritual Intereſt of any; whereas many of all ranks and ages, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs others and diſable themſelves by their Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uries and their Vanities: ſhe contrariwiſe ſpar'd from her ſelf, that she might have the more to give to the neceſſitous, she did ſtudy the Art of Alms-giving, and avoided idle expences, to be rich in good works.</p>
            <p>Her ſweet and mild Diſpoſition, her Charity to all the World, her readineſs to do good where she could, were the features of that Divine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, whereby she reſembled her Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By theſe she indear'd herſelf to thoſe that were bleſt with her converſe, she was Righteous in the full and beſt ſenſe, innocent and beneficient.</p>
            <p>Rejoyce now Bleſſed Soul, with the good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in Heaven, thou that wert a good Angel here below! Let Charity, which upon Earth was thy delight and employment, be thy reward above! enjoy now there that Infinite Goodneſs which here made thee ſo good.</p>
            <p>I run as a man that hath yet a great way to go, and but a short time, you may ſee that I take but here and there a drop out of the full ſtream: But now I aſcend up to the head Spring of it, her Godlineſs, whence iſſued all thoſe Vertues and all that Goodneſs I have mentioned: It was her Love to God, and her deſire to be with him, that made her Live Soberly and Righteouſly, in a manner ſo excellent and ſo exemplary.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:172826:21"/>
            <p> She was well Principled betimes, and upon a good Foundation she erected an excellent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, increaſing in knowledg much faſter than in years; but no Wonder, the Divine Bleſſing could not be wanting where there was great applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and a perſevering diligence to know God and his holy ways, she was doubtleſs a great profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in the Chriſtian School; she read much and with good obſervation: and though being whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intent upon practice, she delighted not in Controverſies, yet she could not only give a good account of the Hope that was in her, but alſo in many things convince gain-ſayers.</p>
            <p>How unprofitably young people ſpend their time, and how much the Study of Religion is neglected in this irreligious Age, is ſufficiently known, though not ſufficiently lamented: but we have here before us an example able to Cure this great Evil, if well attended to. She was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways employ'd in that which was uſeful to her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or others; in learning or in practiſing the beſt of Chriſtian Inſtructions.</p>
            <p>Books were her great delight and recreation; upon them and the poor she could freely beſtow what she ſeemed to grudg to her ſelf, that thoſe Books were not Plays and Romances needs no telling, her Excellent Life declares it. No, they were anſwerable to the great Piety of her conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, they were Books of Religion, and the beſt of that kind; ſuch as grounded her in that Holy Faith she profeſt in the beſt of Churches, ſuch as taught and incited her to diſcharge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172826:21"/> God and man, all the Dutys of a Chriſtian; ſuch as Miniſtred to her Secret and Fervent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions.</p>
            <p>As for the Books of Diſſenters, which might have miſlead or intangled her, she was neither willing nor at leiſure to ſpend any time upon them, she knew she was right, and that the Church is the ſafeſt Guide: therefore her only care was to follow its directions, and to ſee that her works might be anſwerable to her Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The hour of publick Prayer, she expected with longing and great impatience, and she as much Rejoiced when it came: and heartily join'd with the Miniſter who Morning and Evening, did offer the appointed Sacrifice in the Family: and, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Church or at home, ſhe was always careful to be preſent and praying at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, That having (as ſhe ſaid) made her Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Confeſſion, the general Abſolution might be particularly applyed to her Soul.</p>
            <p>She was not of thoſe that count the Church-Offices to be long and tedious, ſhe rather thought they were too ſoon ended, and ſhe would have been griev'd had any of them been omitted. 'Twas her delight to ſee God Worſhipp'd, and to joyn with others in that Bleſſed Imployment; and as if her Heart had not been big enough to entertain thoſe Holy Publick Devotions, which ſhe ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lov'd, she had often a Book of them in her hand, and one to be ſure always about her.</p>
            <p>How Paſſionately did ſhe wiſh alſo for frequent opportunities of receiving the Bleſſed Sacrament,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172826:22"/> and uniting her ſelf in Heart and Myſtery to her deareſt Saviour, as much as is poſſible for us in this life; great was her gladneſs and comfort when thoſe happy ſeaſons return'd, great was her care to put on the wedding-garment, for that Heavenly Marriage-Feaſt. Faſting, Tears and Prayers were the Preparatives; a moſt Humble, Edifying and Devout Behavior were the concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; and a great Love, fervour and gratitude were the ſubſequent Effects of that moſt Solemn Act of Religion.</p>
            <p>If from the Church and the Lords Table, we follow her to her private Cloſet, there we ſhall find her every day ſpend much time in Reading and Meditation, and much more yet upon her knees. No wonder, Bleſſed Soul, if thou wert ſo good, when thou didſt keep ſuch Divine Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny! being always with God, either hearing him ſpeak, or ſpeaking to him; always converſing with Heaven, either in thoughts or words!</p>
            <p>We may yet advance farther to her Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. There we ſhall ſee her alſo much upon her Knees, her Cheeks bedewed with Tears, her mouth filled with the Praiſes of God, and her Heart with his Love, This is the firſt and the laſt thing ſhe doth every day, Nay, days thus Religiouſly ſpent, cannot ſufficiently expreſs that devout affection which her Soul is poſſeſt withal; ſhe defalks as much as ſhe can from the neceſſary refreſhment of Nature; her reſt is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted with acts of adoration, and at mid-night you may find her proſtrate upon the ground,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172826:22"/> watching to God while others ſleep, and antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating, as much as may be, the State of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the Bleſſed imployment of Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>No wonder now, if ſo much Grace inſpired that Soul which ſo much dwelt with God! No wonder if her life and example be bright and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous, as was <hi>Moſes</hi>'s face, when ſhe like him, ſo long convers'd with God! and no wonder if God took her to himſelf betimes, when ſhe like <hi>Enoch</hi> walkt ſo cloſe with him, and with ſo Zealous an aſſiduity.</p>
            <p>Would you think it Chriſtians, if I had not diſcover'd it before, that I have been reading the Life of a young perſon, of one that died under twenty? would you not rather think that I have been making a Collection of all that might be praiſe-worthy in the Lives of many aged good Chriſtians?</p>
            <p>I profeſs I have read the lives of the long Liv'd Fathers of the Deſert; there are in them ſome things very extraordinary, and rather to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at than imitated, but the Life and example of this our younger Saint, is far more inſtructive and edifying than all theirs. She liv'd under no other ingagement than her Baptiſmal Vows, ſhe converſt freely with others, and as to the actions of a civil Life, ſhe willingly complyed with Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Cuſtoms, there was in her nothing extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary but an extraordinary goodneſs and piety.</p>
            <p>And yet it may paſs for a thing very ſingular and hardly to be match't, that where there was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172826:23"/> ſo great a Vertue, ſuch an elevation of mind, there ſhould be no contempt of others, no Pride, no deſire to be obſerv'd; nothing but lowlineſs and the greateſt ſincerity, ſhe did as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> tells of his Siſter, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Seek to approve herſelf only to him who ſees in Secret, and ſhe could have wiſh'd no man had took notice of what ſhe did for God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. <hi>Euge bone ſerve,</hi> well done good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servant, was all the commendation ſhe aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, and if, notwithſtanding her Light did ſhine before men, it was that only God might be glorified.</p>
            <p>Great things have been written of the zeal of retutning Penitents, but ſo much fervour with ſo little Guilt, ſuch an active Piety with ſo much innocence hath ſeldom been ſeen, her Vertue might have been a rich Ornament for gray hairs: but that ſhe ſhould thus intirely devote herſelf to God in the prime of her age, when ſhe might have injoy'd all Humane pleaſures, and was as likely to live long as any one alive: is much to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd and remembred.</p>
            <p>But as ſhe was ſoon ripe and come to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo God ſoon took her from among the chaff, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>and gather'd her with his wheat into his garner.</hi> She went out into her Lords Vinyard, and there began to work from break a day, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would not ſuffer her after ſuch early dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to bear alſo the brunt and the heat of the day, he paid her her wages before Noon, and diſmiſt her to reſt, ſhe ſtarted for the Race, as ſoon as ſhe had enter'd it, and ſhe ran with great ſpeed,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172826:23"/> and therefore ſoon ended her courſe, and betimes received the Crown.</p>
            <p>How ſhe finiſht her Chriſtian Courſe will eaſily be gueſt by what I have already ſaid of its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and progreſs: it could not be with her, as with many remiſs Chriſtians, who, when they approach the confines of Death, begin to mend their pace, and to be very ſerious and active: but ſhe that had liv'd always as if ſhe had been dying, could not but die as ſhe had liv'd.</p>
            <p>Her Body being much a ſtranger to her, and her Soul familiar with God, and always deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Spiritual Pleaſures: she therefore took little Notice of her natural pains and decays: and her infirmities could not oblige her to omit any thing of her wonted Devotions, inſomuch that but little before her laſt Agony, she was two hours upon her knees, taking her farewel of the World, and making her approaches to God in that Devout, Humble poſture, she went an even conſtant pace, and died to God as she had liv'd to him.</p>
            <p>And now, to her I may apply <hi>Philo's</hi> Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he finds that <hi>Abraham</hi> is the firſt in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture called an old man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 8. not but that the Patriarchs before him lived much longer, but becauſe (ſaith he) Age should be reckon'd by Wiſdom and Piety, not by years, by this account we may find alſo that this yong Lady lived long and died full of years, as the Patriach did, her time which she did ſpend ſo Religiouſly to gain
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172826:24"/> bliſsful Eternity cannot be ſaid to have been short.</p>
            <p>And what? shall we now mourn becauſe she is gone from us, or shall we Joy becauſe she is with God? shall we mourn becauſe her Abſence is a grievous loſs: or rejoyce becauſe her Preſence hath been a great and pleaſant advantage? doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a mixture of thoſe two paſſions may here find a place. <hi>Sed ſalva pietate, fidei gaudia praefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi> (ſaid St. <hi>Paulinus)</hi> but without prejudice to Human affection, the joys of Religion should prevail over the Sorrows of Nature, Pſ. 116. 15. <hi>precious in the Sight of the Lord is the death of his Saints:</hi> that which God is delighted with, should not be altogether afflictive to us.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we should not proſecute with ſadneſs and tears the death of Holy Perſons, but rather with Hymns and Acclamations, <hi>cum Canticis &amp; Pſallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium vocibus</hi> as it was the manner of ancient Chriſtians, and even the Decree of a great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, 3<hi>d. Toled.</hi> Rejoycing with them that Rejoyce, congratuling their great Happineſs, becauſe if we follow their Examples; we shall with them be numbred with the Saints of God in Glory Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:172826:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
